[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
computer.org/software. Welcome to
software engineering radio and I'm your
host Joanni. Today I'll be discussing
developing with a camel and zero
frameworks with Malcolm Matala. Malcolm
is the co-founder of Teratim, a CI/CD
solution for Terraform and open to
GitHubs that integrates with GitHub. He
has been developing software since 2002
and he has worked for startups and large
companies across a range of languages,
technologies, and domains. Malcolm,
welcome to Software Engineer Radio. Is
there anything I miss that you'd like to
add? Thank you very much for having me.
I think you hit all the important parts.
Okay, here are some related episodes.
652 Christian Mesh on open tofu 289
James Turnbull on declarative
programming with Terraform and 204 Anil
Medavaped on the mirrage cloud operating
system and the Okamel
language. Now today we'll be talking
about developing with camel and with
zero frameworks which is I would say
quite an unusual approach at least. Yeah
I'd say a little bit too. Yeah and on
both accounts actually. Yes, in both
accounts probably both accounts we would
end of ignite heated conversations among
developers on the choices of language
and the use of frameworks or which
frameworks and all this kind of stuff.
Yeah. Okay. Let's start then giving our
listeners a bit of context and can you
give us a brief description of Teratim
the application we developed in Okamel
with a zero frameworks approach? Yeah,
absolutely. So, Teram is what's called a
tacos in this industry, which is the
infrastructure as code industry and that
stands for Terraform or Tofu as there's
two competing implementations here at
this point, automation and collaboration
software. And essentially what that
means is it's a class of software that
allows users or customers teams to
manage their infrastructure using
Terraform or Open
Tofu collaboratively. In our case that
means that we have chosen to build on
top of VCS providers such as GitHub and
we're also working on GitLab
integration. So all of your
infrastructure management goes through
pull requests. And a core element what
kind of makes us different from other
providers in this space is that we
believe you should never have to leave
your normal comfortable development
workflow to use the product to make to
complete the tasks you want to complete.
We try to integrate into your existing
workflows. So for example, if you are
creating a Kubernetes cluster, you would
probably write some Terraform code to
represent that. And then if you're using
Terror Team, you'd make a pull request
and then Terror team would pick up that
event on GitHub and perform what's
called a plan operation to say if you
want to execute this change, here are
the things that I will do to make that
happen. And then the rest of your team
can go and review that output and give
you approval. And once you have that
approval, you can choose to apply that
change, which means make that change
into reality and then merge it into your
main branch and then continue on. And
for Ter team, all that happens inside
of, in this case, GitHub. Okay. What
were the main issues driving your
decision about the choice of language
and the evidence of frameworks as well?
So, I'll say to start out with, I think
it's really important to understand that
context matters a lot when you're making
technical decisions. And what I mean by
that
is I personally believe that at the end
of the day, the difference between
choosing different technical stacks is
relatively marginal compared to other
decisions. And and so what that means is
if you choose Python or Okamel, I don't
think it's going to make a huge
difference at the end of the day. But
what does matter is if the people that
are working in that codebase enjoy using
that or can think in the way that that
codebase supports. So for example,
Okamel is a statically typed language
and it's strongly typed. Uh you can kind
of think of it, but uh people might
think of Haskell. So it's very similar
to hasll o camel but it's not it's it's
a little bit more practical I would say
but it has if you looked at two files
you would probably from the surface say
they're very similar and for me I think
in a statically typed language so what
that means for example is I might choose
to represent let's take something simple
like the zip code I might create a type
that represents a zip code and then I
might have functions that guarantee that
if you give me a string that you say is
a zip code, it enforces that that
actually is a zip code. And now that we
have successfully constructed a type of
zip code, I can pass it around my
codebase and nobody else has to verify,
oh, is this actually a zip code or not?
So, it's no longer a string. It might be
a string in the computer, but it's not a
string in the code. And so, for me,
that's a way I like to think about
problems. I like to say how can I take
this external input a user and turn it
into a type in the program and then what
operations can I do on that type and
that is harder to do in a language for
example like Python where you don't
really have a compiler enforcing types
for you and you have to go through more
tests for example or understand your
program at a different level. So at the
end of the day, if you are very
proficient in Python, great, use Python.
If you're very proficient at something
else like Rust, great, use Rust. For me,
I really enjoy writing Okamel. And when
I wake up in the morning and I have a
problem to solve and I know I'm going to
be able to solve it in Okamel, to me,
that is like a strong motivator. So to
start out with, like choose your text
stack for something that you enjoy
doing. So that's where we got started
with Okamel is I've been a longtime
Okamel
developer. Probably the path I took was
starting out with actually PHP and then
moving on to Python after that and then
playing around with C and
C++ and eventually making my way to
Okamel as I like started thinking more
about types and how they express my
program. So I've been working in Oakamel
for probably 15 years before we founded
Terror
Team. And part of that
was I have kind of a guess like either a
naive or an arrogance around like how
hard can that be to do? So I see a
problem and I it looks hard. I'm like
come on that can't be that hard. It's
just software, right? Okamel is kind of
like the wild west in that there's a lot
of competition there on how to do things
and there's a lot of really smart people
and one of the things there that's very
common is there's multiple standard
libraries and there's multiple
frameworks on how to express concurrent
operations and what I mean by that is
you might have to do multiple HTTP
requests and if you are not using some
sort of concurrency system or
parallelism system you'd have to do one
request followed by the other. But if
you have some sort of concurrency
framework, you can say do both of these
at the same time. Okay. What about the
rest of the team? So you really like
Okamel. You're a longtime Okamel
programmer. So were you already working
with other people that are in the same
space then they they use Okamel as their
main language? Not so much. I was
definitely prior to terror team. I was
doing okamel more in passion projects
and a lot of the software that we use in
terror team is stuff that I wrote as
part of these passion projects. There is
it's called uh CUFP which is the
commercial users of functional
programming which is a yearly conference
part of another larger functional
programming conference and that's where
a lot of the industrial people get
together to talk about what they're
doing and a lot of hobbyists as well but
I had never worked professionally as O
camel before ter. Okay. But you found
other people that had the same share the
same passion with o camel or Yeah. Yeah.
I know it's I would say it's a small but
really good community and I don't know
about you but for me there's sort of
this inflection point where a community
becomes too big and I
find it's hard to be a member of it
because you a lot of communities get
like their their small core people where
like those are the thought leaders in it
and then everyone else either just is
listening to it or it's hard to have
like a discussion about these
complicated things. For example, if you
look at like a lot of Reddit subreddits,
you go to any uh post on there and it
already has like 2,000 comments and it's
hard to to have like a deep nuance
conversation there in my opinion. But
the old community is smaller such that
there's a mailing list and then also um
a discourse for it and it's small enough
that there's a lot of really good really
good back and forth communication with a
lot of people discussing how to do
things, the future of the project. So
you can really have kind of a big impact
in Okamel because it still is this core
group of people. It's definitely growing
and we're actually getting um this week
there was pretty long discourse thread
sort of comparing ways that Go does
things better for a newbie than Okamel
does and what things we could consider
incorporating into future versions of
the language to make it more friendly to
beginners.
Okay, understand. So if I can summarize
is the choice of Okamel was due to the
fact that you like Okamel. You've been a
longtime Okamel user even if it was for
passion projects only but also the
community is made is a small community
with passionate people and probably
clever people that somehow you enjoy
interacting with is is active and you
can have a voice. So this basically you
like the technology and the context
around it because you said before
otherwise you know could have chosen any
other language pretty much to solve the
same problem. Yeah. Is this am I
understanding? Yeah. Well one thing to
add to that is I also feel very
confident solving problems in Okamel
like if you give me a problem I feel
very confident that I'll be able to
solve it in a reasonable amount of time
and okay. Okay. And going back to the
zero frameworks approach why what were
the the what were the issues you are
trying to solve with this why you said
okay I don't want to use any frameworks
or teratin so the origin of that comes
from just working with other frameworks
in the past I don't want to throw it
under the bus but I've worked quite a
bit with Django in the past so that's
probably the one of the main sources and
for
me I found that a framework like Django.
What? Let me go back one step. Let me
say what is a framework? So for the
purposes of this conversation, a
framework is a library where it makes
flow control decisions about your
code. So rather than you calling the
framework, you say, "Hey framework, when
an HTTP request happens, call this thing
that I wrote and then go and route that
to something else, etc." So it's the one
making the flow the control flow
decisions. So my experience with Django
was
pretty not great in that I found that I
spent a lot of time debugging the
framework and fighting the framework
rather than solving the problem I had.
And part of that could have been that
I'm just not thinking in the right way
that I'm coming at it from a different
angle and there's this impedance
mismatch between me and Django.
But that really led me to sort of like I
was talking about before, but I think
how hard could this be? I was like,
okay, well, I want to write things my
way for the use cases I have. And that
was the first passion project on
starting to write a lot of
backend libraries and our own frameworks
for how to solve common problems. For
example, HTTP request
route. So, it isn't to say terror team
doesn't have frameworks. It's that we
don't take frameworks in as a
dependency, but we're okay taking
libraries in as a dependency because
they don't control the flow control of
your program. And that means changing
out a library for a different library is
quite easy. Changing out a framework for
a different framework essentially is
rewriting your
program. And there's a few real key
benefits there. One is that we are in
complete control over the destiny of
that software. So we're not caught into
another piece of software's release
cycle or when they decide to deprecate
certain features that we might actually
find
valuable. Also, our framework only does
the things we need it to do. So there's
never communitydriven functionality in
there that we don't consume but may
interact negatively with things we're
trying to do. And for us, we are a
bootstrapped company. We're pretty lean.
And having the ability to choose when we
want
to make changes like that to our
software is really important. We don't
want to have to be running up against
like a long-term support deadline like
deprecation for framework we depend on
and being forced to do a big rewrite of
our software because of someone else's
decision. Okay.
So when you say zero frameworks, you
mean zero frameworks as in frameworks
developed outside your team, things you
depend upon, but within your development
environment you created your own
frameworks to solve your own problems.
Yeah. Okay. So basically said the zero
frameworks mean we don't get any of
those in but we create the ones we need
that are perfectly suitable for the
things we need because we are making
them for that reason. Exactly. Exactly.
Okay. And also when you say zero
frameworks you mean absolutely none nada
nil it's like or maybe use some I don't
know for um unit testing framework to
run your tests or something else I mean
is is zero an absolute zero or or is
almost there but not I would say
99.9% zero we do have our own testing
harness and I actually go back and forth
on whether that is something that we
should use that someone else made or
whether we should maintain that
ourselves. Currently, we don't have a
problem with it. So, it just works. So,
there's no real motivation there.
But when it comes to
production, the only external framework
we use is one that handles HTTP parsing
for us and construction of queries. And
that
particular framework was written in a
way where it's quite easy to make it be
consumed by your own system. So it was
done in a way where we can integrate it
into what we have very easily and if
something better comes along, we've
designed our integration in a way where
we could flip it out pretty easily. So
you you wrapped it you wrapped the
framework behind your own
implementation. Put a facade in front of
it include your own application. Yeah.
Yeah. And and that's really because HP
parsing is complicated enough where we
didn't want
to deal with that to be honest and other
people can definitely do that better.
But also there was an existing solution
that we knew we could integrate into our
system in a way where we felt confident
we could remove it if wanted. Okay. So
zero is not exactly zero. Yeah. Yeah.
Slightly bigger than that but it's
sufficiently close to call it zero. I
think this is an
interesting growth as a software
engineer. So when I was younger and even
more obstinate, I probably would have
been much more this is the rule, we
follow the rule. And just the softness
of age and experience has said we have
rules of thumb and they're great rules
of thumb, but context really does matter
a lot and we have to choose in the
situations use our context to decide
what the best option. Yeah. Yeah. Well,
I I agree with that and I also know that
the choice of framework sometimes is not
made thinking deeply enough, especially
in situations where you have several
frameworks in a single application. They
may actually compete for the control
flow of the application creating all
sorts of problems and and then you end
up saying, "Oh, well, I'll spawn this
one in one thread and this one in the
other and hope I never have to
communicate between the two of them
because who knows what's going to happen
there.
Yeah. So it's it's definitely uh
understandable. Yeah. Yeah. So we have
both backend frameworks and front-end
frameworks. So one thing that's cool
about Okamel is there is a compiler from
Okamel to
JavaScript. So that means a lot of our
libraries end up getting used in both
contexts.
And for example, our API definition is
Okamel code and we just compile it to
JavaScript for the front end and to
machine code for the back end. And we
know it's always communicating with each
other using the same exact API
definition. That's one example. That is
actually interesting because before when
you mentioned Okamel chosen as a as as
the language because you liked it mostly
say any other language would have worked
the same. But if you chose for example
C++ doing the back end bit would have
been easy but then for the front end
probably would have would have to use
something else maybe JavaScript or
TypeScript or Yeah. Yeah. Or or at least
I I know you can compile C++ to
JavaScript but you at least would have
probably had to put pieces around it in
another language to make it integrate in
there. Where camel you get it's a direct
mapping to JavaScript. There's actually
there's a few competing options there
actually. We use one called JS of Okamel
which is meant to be more ergonomic for
the Okamel developer. So it cares less
about JavaScript and it says we're just
going to take how you want to write
Okamel and turn into JavaScript.
Facebook a while ago came up with what's
called reason ML which is a dialect of
okamel and it interrops with okamel but
it is designed to compile into more
human readable JavaScript and it so it
has more of a direct mapping to
JavaScript but all that is built on top
of okamel and compiles okamel integrates
with all okamel so Facebook chose the
path of we think it's important to be
more close to JavaScript whereas the
path we've chosen is we want to be
closer to okamel also be able to use it
in these JavaScript contexts. Okay.
Okay. Yeah. But I can see the advantages
of this approach when you have to
communicate before sorry between and
front end. It's also for uh again a lean
team. I think there's a lot of value in
not having to context switch between
languages. Yeah. Yeah. Definitely. Also,
this is an question that just came to my
mind. Also in this l team you do back
end front end but you don't have
specialized front end or back end
developers in this context. Everybody
can do pretty much everything. Yep. Our
engineering team is me and one other
person. Yeah.
Okay. So it's it's extremely lean. Yeah.
Very lean. Very lean. I will say that
our stylesheets probably suffer a little
bit from being so lean. I don't have
necessarily an eye for a a beautiful
front end, but it's functional and it
works.
And for using Okamel, what tools are
around there that can make your life
easier? If you chose Java for example,
an idea that everybody uses is probably
Intelligj or maybe not everybody but
most people. Yeah, with refactoring
capabilities and all sorts of nice
things to navigate, code and manipulate
it easily. What is the standard in
Okamel? So for me, I'm on Emacs, but a
lot of people use Visual Studio, which
has really good Okamel support. And I
think part of that is because Facebook
has been such a large or meta now, I
guess, has been such a large user of
Okamel. They developed a lot of tooling
around there. But you know, the recent
development in developing in the last 10
years has been LSPs. And that I think
has been fantastic for a lot of people
in the sense that I no longer have to
choose a special IDE to get great
functionality for a language. So I use
Emacs and I have all the same access to
the LSP functionality that a Visual
Studio user has. So you really you can
do refactorings and navigate your code
easily. Yeah. Yeah. So I mostly use it
for the navigation, searching through
it, looking at what a type is. So like I
said, OKL is a strongly typed language
and once you start getting into that
mindset, you encode a lot of information
in the type. So, if you have an
expression that you're looking at, it's
really valuable to put your cursor over
it and see what the resulting type is
because that just tells you a whole lot
about the context of that code and
what's going on and how the author
planned on using that value that they've
expressed. Yeah. Yeah. I think all
expressing everything in types like
this, I think in some circles are called
also microtypes like the example you
gave of the zip code before. Yeah. Yeah.
So you can keep it as a string and then
check every time that is actually a
valid zip code. Yeah. Or you can do a
small type that is basically pass the
string, build it, check that the format
is correct and then pretty much that you
know and pass that around. Yeah. I I I
remember a very small so this was such a
small example and of a place where I was
using Python and I was just like man I
wish I had a strong static type language
here was forget the actual program we're
doing doesn't matter but the point is we
had a function that was receiving
something that looked that was iterable
like a list as input and a precondition
we wanted was that that list needed to
have all duplicates removed so it needed
to be set in
reality and it's kind of an anti-attern
in Python to check what type something
is. You really should be oh can I just
iterate through it? You know it's the
duct typing thing but it was really
important in this case that it was
actually had duplicates removed and our
only option was just to check each time
to essentially we convert the iterable
to a set and then use that set going
going around. But I was like what why do
I have to do that? because other parts
of the code could already have made that
guarantee for us. And this is something
where it it's a little paper cut I'll
say that adds up when you just think of
all the different places you're doing
things like that when if you could just
say it's a set and then that function
consumes a set the end. Yeah. in terms
of framework. So you said that well
apart from the one framework for HTTP
parsing you developed the other ones
including the unit testing one you said
but how far did you go? So do you spend
a lot of time developing internal
frameworks for your system or you need
only only some? At this point we don't
spend much time doing it at all. I would
say the deepest we've gone is we have
our own Postgress driver as well. Wow,
that that's why did you do that? Well,
so we well actually is that thus went.
So I guess even the further layer down
is we have our own concurrency framework
which that's what I said it's the one
that says I want to do two things at the
same time. Let me express that and then
give me the result. And part of that
means if you want to go up from there so
that's the base level. And so the next
level up from there for us is we want to
interact with the database. We
implemented our own database driver. And
that's actually broken up into two
parts. One is what we call a codec which
is what parses the bytes and the way
that works is it's actually it's a
library. So you have some other piece of
code that reads bytes and then it hands
it to the codec and the codec says okay
you've given me enough bytes to consume
uh we call them frames and here's the
decoded one go do what you want with it
and then keep on giving me more bytes
and then oh you've given me a frame you
want to turn into bytes here's the bytes
for that frame so that's a library and
so anyone could actually use that if
they wanted to build their own Postgress
driver but then on top of that you have
the Postgress protocol which is say says
even if we have these frames what's the
order they have to happen in if I send
you this frame what do you have to
respond with and that one does integrate
into our concurrency frame so for the
listener who's thinking oh this guy did
it that's great I can go do it I I want
to be really clear that a lot of this
was work I was doing on my own before
founding the company we wouldn't have
done this if we had to develop the
frameworks and found the company at the
same time okay that's interesting What
would they have done instead? If we I
think we might have used some existing
frameworks that are in the OK world. I
would have tried to stay in the OK world
if we couldn't find what we wanted
there, which I think is unlikely. I
think we probably would have gone
either we would have looked at
architectures that might simplify at the
expense of performance using like
perhaps we could have used like even
like CGI or something like that with a
phone behind it and then worst case look
at another language option. For me my
next language would probably be Python.
Even though I'm not a huge Python fan, I
absolutely accept that it has its
benefits and it has its purposes and I
am proficient in it. So that would have
probably been the the plan D or E in
that case. Okay, that seems to tying
with the context that you mentioned a
few times. In this case, the context of
when you founded the company, what you
got what you had available. Yeah. So, I
mean, I'd spent almost 10 years just for
fun developing these tools on my own to
solve problems how I think they should
be solved. And I'd been developing a
bunch of personal projects with those
tools. Some of them I was trying to turn
into a company, but just the idea didn't
work out. And so, once we got to the
point of making terror team, I felt
really confident that what I had written
was production ready and we could go
with that. And I think that that has
been one way we've managed to really
truly stay lean. There are there's been
a few times where we have bugs in a
framework and because I've written
pretty much every line, I know exactly
where to go to start looking at what's
going on there. Another benefit we have
which this is nothing to do with your
own frameworks or not but we are
monorreo company so we have everything
in the same repo and with our own
frameworks in that repo it's nice where
if you need to just add some sort of
debugging statement somewhere really low
in the stack you just do it recompile
and run and you're good and I so for me
I'm very into monor repos as well
okay I think the value there on debug
bugging is just so high where if you're
trying to manage your dependency manager
to get your own custom version of some
low-level dependency in there, you end
up going through in my opinion a lot
more trouble than it's worth. H the the
monor repo you chose the monor repo in
all this context with okamo no
frameworks monor repo all with something
in mind in terms of how to manage the
system develop it and debug it in a way
that is easy for you I took a lot of
inspiration actually from
SQLite where
they are I mean he's gone even further
than me where he has his own git
replacement or manage managing SQL light
but they are very much into everything
is you have to treat it as a whole
system and you have to think about how
all this
interacts and yes it this one thing
might solve your immediate problem now
but how is that going to affect when you
get a customer support call and you're
trying to figure out why this weird
interaction happened but you don't
control how those interactions happen
you end up having to learn someone
else's code on the fly rather than
having gone in designing it So that is I
if you can do that, if you can be there
when the time is right where you have
all this tooling and now you have an
idea you can execute on. I think the the
benefit of being able to understand your
whole system and know what each piece is
doing and being able to jump in when you
have a usually when I get a a support
issue, I know roughly where in the stack
that that issue is and like almost down
to the file that I need to look at to
think about what the how to address it.
Yeah, I think some frameworks are
actually good in this as well because
they give you hooks for observability
purposes. Basically check into them, but
I don't think they are the majority yet.
Many of them work in obscure ways when
you have defects or issues and it's
really difficult to figure things out.
Yeah. Yeah. And and a lot of popular
frameworks are popular because they
provide a lot of use cases to a lot of
people. And that means a lot more code
and a lot more both positive and
negative customizability where you have
all these hooks to do different things
but you also have to understand how to
use all those hooks a lot of
documentation there. So again that that
can be the right choice in your context
depending on what what what you're
doing. But I think if if anything,
whether you want to do frameworks or not
do your own frameworks, I think our
industry would benefit from thinking
about our applications as whole systems
and less about this one ticket I'm
working on or this one component I'm
working on or just writing the code
versus maintaining the code in the
future. Yeah. with the approach you
chose. So I'm curious to know you know
what worked well a bit of hindsight if
you like. So you already said you know
Okamel was the right tool for the job
because you knew the language very well.
We've been working that for quite some
time. You mentioned well the strong
typing is was a must anyway. So I would
imagine that if you chose another
language would have been something with
strong typing or at least strong enough.
with C++ it's difficult to say that is
very strongly typed
sometimes but also you mentioned the
fact that you can compile into
JavaScript so this allows you to use one
tool for back end and front end and also
use well share lots of the same
structures in the communication but is
there are there any other advantages
that you found out using Okamel I mean
this these are already quite a few but
I'm wondering if there is something else
I think
that this isn't something going into it
I was thinking deeply about. But I will
say that I think the Okamel community is
at
a sort of a a size
where there are actually a lot of
library choices
for consuming different integrations or
different file formats. So, I think
that one thing you can get stuck on if
you're going to build a lot of stuff
yourself is if you're doing a lot of
integrations, getting stuck on other
people's APIs and having to implement
that or if you're doing data related
things, having to consume different file
formats and especially file formats that
aren't
super strict. So I I can think like CSV
comes to mind where there's this concept
of a CSV file, but how you escape like a
comma inside of a cell really depends on
what tool is being used or it may be
that there's a slight variations there.
So for us since we are happy to consume
libraries, the Okimo world actually is
big enough where there are a lot of
libraries for different things we want
to work with.
So there are for example there are other
Postgress libraries. So there was a
place where I could go and look at other
implementations and think about how they
were doing it. Maybe there's some
interesting parsing going on there that
I had to figure out on my own. And
there's a pretty
good encryption world in Okamel for some
reason. I think it's because actually
there's a large number of
cryptocurrencies developed on Okamel. So
the crypto libraries are actually pretty
solid. And so one thing that we do quite
a bit actually is we our API is based on
you request a token that is signed by a
server and then you pass that around to
do different other API requests. Yeah.
Okay. But for example, if you are really
into sort of a less well-known language,
take one type of like icon or something
like that or even SML which is kind of
related to Okamel. I think you might
struggle. You might be able to you will
be able to do your own frameworks, I
think, but you might struggle when you
come into contact with the real world
and what APIs or file formats exist out
there depending on what problem you're
trying to solve.
Mhm. And what about zero frameworks
approach again? So we mentioned the
issues with depending on external
frameworks potentially also several of
them that each of them trying to manage
the flow of control of your application
maybe in competing ways but also
upgrades and anything else related to
outside dependencies pretty much. Are
there any other advantages that you
found out that you were not thinking
about when you started with the zero
frameworks approach? So coinciding with
the monor repo choice, I think the
ability to have all of your code post at
hand was not something that I went into
it expecting to be such a huge win. So I
knew that it was important for us for
for my programs for me to be able to
control the flow of it entirely. But I
didn't necessarily go in with the idea
of being a monor repo. But once
essentially I started building out some
frameworks and then I was like all right
well I want to use this for something so
I'm just going to put the application in
next to the framework so it's easy
because I know there's going to be a lot
of back and forth there. And then as I
started iterating on that, I was like,
"Wow, it's really easy." If I if I have
a bug that I think is framework related,
it's just right next to it. And I can
treat that task the exact same way I
would treat an application task in terms
of the code change. And I think that is
something that I did not expect going
into this, but turns out to be really
really valuable. Yeah. Also, I what I
would expect is that if the application
grows a lot or maybe a different kind of
application with a lots of microservices
and whatnot, you probably would need to
develop some tools around them to manage
the monor repo itself. You probably
wouldn't like to check out 20 GB of code
to change one service. Well, to to go
back to being lean, we uh one thing we
do is we implement a monolith. a
monolith in terms of the binary that you
get out of it. But the the code
structure and the architecture of the
code is very is split out into
components of course. But everything
does compile down into one single
binary. But
being with the goal of being lean, that
also forces constraints on you to think
about the scale that you want to attack
problems at. I give you example. So
right now we're a feature that we want
is when we run people's terraform code,
sometimes it generates artifacts that
you need between a plan step and an
apply step. And in our case, we run all
of the operations on ephemeral compute.
So you get a brand new computer every
time you perform an operation. There's a
little bit of state. Sometimes you want
to keep them. So we
are implementing a simple key value
store
API that uh the users will be able to
upload a small artifact to and then pull
it out the other side. And so we're
going this knowing that one, we're not
going to be S3. We don't want to be S3.
We don't need to handle a billion
requests per second or whatever they're
doing. And we're okay making tradeoffs
for simplicity and for staying small and
lean and for
debugability that I think if you want to
have a company or product operating at a
different scale, you might not be able
to make those same decisions that we
are. Yeah.
Yeah. And now another question with the
always with the hindsight. What did not
work so well? Are there any aspects of
the application for which okamel was
less suitable than other languages?
The space that we're in is very
Goheavy
and that means that there's a lot of
tooling that's written in Go
that we cannot or there's libraries
written in Go that we can't easily
interact with because we're
OAML. And so there is some functionality
that becomes a question of do we need to
wrap this go library in something else
that for example maybe communicates over
standard in and standard out or do we
want to implement our own version of
that go library. An example here is we
have a small feature where we index your
Terraform code and Terraform has a
concept of modules and you can say okay
for this place use this shared piece of
code in another directory or in another
you can pull it off the internet as
well. And for the case where that module
is located in the same repository as the
code using it, you want it to function
such that if you update the module,
everyone who uses that module gets a
plan and apply operation performed on
it. You want to see the actual output
there. So we have a way to manually
express that in our product, but also we
wanted a way to automatically do it so
people could be more dynamic. And that
involves parsing what's called HCL or
Hashi Corp config
language. And it's a pretty simple
language, but there's a Go library that
does it of course because Terraform and
Tofu are written in Go. So they have to
do it. So it's just there. And we in
that case we made the decision that we
wanted to write our own parser because
we think that is a stepping stone to
doing more complicated things in HCL and
we wanted that functionality there for
ourselves but there's other linting
operations that so for we don't consume
the state or plan we don't have parsers
for those yet and there are parsers of
course in go and we aren't sure whether
that's something important enough to us
where we want to implement it in Okamel
or we want to look at how could we wrap
that in a go CLI or something like that
or how to integrate
that. So in our case it's kind of like
the underlying challenge is the space is
in a language that we're not using and
so there is a little impedance mismatch.
Additionally, we are open- source. So
being an Okamel doesn't necessarily
attract go
programmers. So depending on how we want
to interact with the community, Okamel
can be kind of a stumbling block for
getting contributions. H actually this
is interesting because assuming that
you'll be wildly successful and the
company will grow. This I think will
pose interesting problems in terms of
hiring
people finding developers that want to
to work in Okamel. I mean just for for
the fact that the community is small
compared to other language communities.
Yeah. My my opinion there and this
hasn't been tested yet. We're starting
to get to the point we're going to grow
our engineering team
more. But my view is that if you're
trying to stay relatively small and
lean, you want to grow maybe an engineer
every year or
two, as long as you can attract someone
to it and you're willing to invest in
long-term success for them, then the
training them up on all of this is not a
big challenge. So, we don't really
expect to have to hire people
necessarily from inside the El Camel
world. We're happy to train them and
everything they need to know. And
especially this because we've
implemented so much of our own code,
they would want to be trained up in
those specifics anyways.
So I I think if you're an Uber or some
other company that is trying to hit
hyperrowth, this is definitely not
something like Okamel, you are going to
struggle to get people that can hit the
ground running. But if you are a company
that's willing to invest a lot in the
training and long-term success of
employees, I am less concerned of that
for the for the future of the company.
Yeah. and and also you might be able to
actually you know grow the business
without hiring hundreds of developers
anyway. Yeah. Yeah. I I saw I think
recently that blue sky the entire
engineering department was 15
people running the show. I mean it's
millions of users. So it's Yeah. Yeah.
And I don't I don't remember how big
WhatsApp was but it was double digits
right? And all that was in Erling which
is a relatively small language as well
on the scale of okamel. So yeah so maybe
you know maybe a problem or maybe not.
Yeah I was talking to so in the journey
of us deciding to go open source. We
talked to a lot of people because we
were just terrified that if we went open
source all of our revenue would
disappear and you know we what would we
do then? So I talked to some other
people that were in the open source
world and I talked to Adam Jacob of Chef
and he's actually in the infrastructure
world now too with system in it
and Chef actually had a lot of Erlang in
it which again is one of those more
esoteric languages not a huge community
and I asked him about contributors and
his response was you might actually get
a ton of contributions when you go open
source because what happened in Chef is
there's all these hobbyist Erling people
who are so happy to see a production
piece of software written in their
favorite language and they just jump on
it and just want to like they want to
change the world, right? So, they want
to implement as many pull requests as
they can to be part of that. So, they're
just super happy to see something that
is out there that the rest of the world
is using. That's interesting. Becomes a
win-win situation though. Exactly. for
the company and the community of people
that are actually interested in these
well let's say esoteric languages they
don't find a lot to contribute to it so
they jump on what is available and I I
don't know if you remember the what is
it called the blood paradox article from
Paul Graham where essentially he makes
this argument about I think it's about
Python at the time this is how old that
article is where Python was kind of a
nothing language and he said look go
find Python programmer mers cuz those
are people really passionate about the
technology space and they're probably
really into that language. So, they're
going to know it really really well.
And because they're willing to be off in
this other space, they're probably going
to be forget the exact language he uses,
but kind of like more thoughtful about a
lot of stuff and have thought through a
lot of things because they're making
this explicit decision to go a different
path. Yeah. What about the framework? So
again, have you found situations in
hindsight you say, "Oh gosh, we should
have used a framework, an outside
framework here because we are spending,
I don't know, an inordinate amount of
time solving this problem
or any other reason." So it's not
something where it's such a painoint
where I just wish we didn't do it. But
one thing we have is a JSON schema
compiler to Okamel. So we generate o
camel code from a JSON schema. So for
example, we use that because we have our
we do a lot of GitHub API calls and I
didn't want to have to write the API out
for all of those. So and GitHub nicely
they publish a JSON schema for the
entire API but it's huge. And so I
decided to write a JSON schema code
generator for that. And that is
something where I didn't sufficiently
learn JSON schema before writing it
where the tool I wrote isn't just kind
of like a
mess. So when I have to go and fix a
bug, I'm just sort of like dreading that
piece of code if I ever come across it.
And there's a few things that I know I
want to do in there to make life a
little bit easier and I just don't want
to do it because that code is just so
messy and gnarly. And it works good
enough where I'm just sort of like don't
touch it. I'll deal with this other pain
point on the other side of like
consuming this library. And we do a lot
of JSON schema stuff just cuz JSON's you
know what the internet speaks. And
especially when we're adding new
integrations, we try to find a JSON
schema if we can find it, or we'll write
our own JSON schema if we can't find one
out there. So, this one little tool ends
up getting used in orderly large amount
of time and it has like the most little
pain points in it. I've got the feeling
that you'll have to bite the bullet
sooner. Yeah, I think so. I think so.
and take it. I will say we probably have
the most complete GitHub API client. I
think it's 3 megabytes of code is what
gets outputed. It takes 10 minutes to
compile from
scratch. And that is just for the
parsing. We can go both ways. We can
parse requests and generate requests as
well. Ah, okay. We also found some
interesting um places where the GitHub
API doesn't agree with its own JSON
schema.
Well, that happens, too. Yeah, that was
the best of us. Yeah, I've seen other
other situations where that where that
was the case.
In terms of lessons learned, yeah, so
lessons learned so far at least. Yeah.
By using this approach, are there any
lessons that you think can be applied to
other context and systems? Yeah.
So for example, how did avoidance of
frameworks affect timelines or other
other considerations in general? Any
lessons you think could be applied to
other context or systems? I think that
for timelines, having our own frameworks
has actually helped us be more
consistent in predicting them because we
kind of know that there aren't there
isn't this rabbit hole where you're
trying to do something that seems easy.
Then you realize the framework that you
are using doesn't really do it. We kind
of we know what our frameworks can and
can't do. And very rarely does it turn
out we want to add this feature that
ends up becoming this huge modification
of a framework. It's really nice in that
way.
Definitely again like I I really can't
stress it enough to anyone listening is
just don't go into this being like it
worked for this guy and worked for me as
well. Really be thoughtful about what
you want to get out of it. But also I I
think there's there's the only internet
talking points of what's called NIH
syndrome, right? Like not invented here.
And I think definitely pay attention
what people are saying in those cases. I
I think maybe our industry is a little
too focused on you need to consume
dependencies and somebody else has
written that better than you have and
it's better off using it. I think you
have to be more thoughtful there and you
shouldn't be afraid of implementing
something yourself as long as you can
convince yourself that you're getting
out of doing that work what you want to
get out of it. And also look back on it
like if you did implement something and
you realize actually this wasn't the
right choice then like use that
information for the next time but don't
let like these uh there's so many
acronyms in our world of like Yagy and
NIH and all that and I think I think we
would benefit in general being more
thoughtful about that because definitely
for like me talking to other developers
you get this this resistance when you
start talking about oh I did this myself
did that myself, we have this, we own
that
and look at it really as the whole
system. Like you really have to think
about as the whole system and there's
definitely gains to be made when we
start doing more system level in this
industry. Yeah. And I think also when
you work on the systems you can still
put safety guards there like when you
said you use a the HTTP parsing but you
put a facade on it so it doesn't pollute
your system. So if that library is not
maintained anymore or use something that
is better, you just need to change that
and the connections to it. But the rest
of the application will be unaffected.
So we can still protect ourselves
against some choices or make new choices
later. I think again yeah and so I I
sort of poo pooed on Django earlier in
this but you know if Django is the right
choice for you that's fine. We're
certainly an extreme example of the
degree that we've implement our all of
our own technology, but that doesn't
have to be true for everyone. There
could be certain things where this is
actually really important that we own
this piece, but how HTB requests are
routed is not important to us. We just
need it to work. And that's that's
great. And I guess this applies to
pretty much everything. So even choosing
choosing the language, choosing the
framework, anything. So look at the
context where you are and take a
decision based on that. I guess. Yeah.
Something that I've definitely learned
in my career and I I used to be very
opinionated about, oh, you should use
this because that's no good or choose
this because it's way better. And like I
said, I've softened up a lot where I
think what your team or yourself are
most effective in and also just enjoy
using day in and day out. Even if it is,
you know, for all the the technical
metrics a less optimal choice, it might
be the more optimal choice for social
reasons. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. This this is
interesting because it's one of those
things that
you those thoughts that come to your
head after a few years of experience
because I think each of us when we were
at the beginning made decisions based on
the perfect framework perfect language
obvious solution without thinking about
any social aspects at all focusing on
the tool the maybe the nominal
performances of the tool. I worked a lot
in C++ in the past. You know, it was
many people wanted to be close to the
metal to go fast without even knowing if
they needed to go that fast or if they
were able to go fast in the first place.
There is simple as but Yeah. Yeah. So
sometimes we need to broaden the context
and
understand a bit more than the technical
aspects. Yeah. And I think that just
because we're people as well, there's
always going to be fads in languages.
There's going to be I mean there's a
huge thing of rewrite everything in
Rust, right? And it's there's a lot of
blog posts around that and there's a lot
of good reasons to do that and there's a
lot of not good reasons to do that. So
don't going against the grain on
decisions is not inherently a sign that
you're not making the right choice.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I
agree. I agree. Yeah. Well, thank you. I
think you gave us a lot of food for
thought
today. So, is there anything else that
we missed that you wouldd like to add?
Like I said, we're open source. That
means we're a monor repo. So, you can go
and look at all I've talked about. If
you go to our website and use the link
to GitHub there, you can see all that.
And I will say I so I'm proud of the
code in there, but I also am realistic
in that there's a lot of sharp edges.
There's a lot of stuff in there that
works because I know how it works and it
works for me and somebody coming in they
might be like well that's a strange
decision and I and I do know there's
places where oh it breaks down here and
here's where you got to be a little
little careful in using it. So I I'm not
going to say this is like production
ready for other people. It's definitely
production ready for us. Yeah. Well, and
and nobody will be able to criticize
your code about the JSON parser because
you already said that it's problematic.
But the reality is that in any in any
software system, you end up with parts
of the code that are not the the best
the best code you could possibly write
for a variety of reasons.
Yeah. I mean, going back to the
experience breeds wisdom idea is I
remember being young and looking at
other people's code and being very
critical of it. And now that I'm there,
I'm like, all right, well, I know why
those decisions were made and sometimes
those are the right decisions. I had to
pay beers to colleagues once criticizing
some code I saw. I was really upset with
them only to find out that it was the
code that I wrote a few months earlier.
I I think many of us make this mistake.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you very much Malcolm for
coming to the show and it has been a
pleasure. Thank you very much. This is
Joavanny for Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at
se-radio.net. To provide feedback, you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack
channel at
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamseradio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
Creative Common License
2.5. Thanks for listening. Let's go.